[Music]
this film is part of rebel wisdoms
series the science and psychology of
polarization Peter Levine is known as a
revolutionary figure in the world of
personal growth since the 1970s he's
been working on a set of theories about
how the body stores emotion and trauma
that became the field of somatic
experiencing his breakthrough book was
called waking the tiger he realized how
animals naturally shake off traumatic
experiences to return to normal but how
humans most often stop this natural
healing process leaving trauma locked in
the body together with Bessel Vander
Kolk and Steven Porges their work
revolutionized the world of trauma
showing how as Bessel Vander Kolk lassic
book explained the body keeps the score
and that many mental issues had their
roots in unprocessed sensations and
emotions in the body where did this work
originate from it was a gradual
evolution really beginning in the mid
1960s but there was a seminal event that
occurred in 1969 and I write about that
in waking the tiger where I was asked to
see this woman I call her Nancy who had
been suffering from all kinds of
physical complaints what we would now
call fibromyalgia chronic fatigue
irritable bowel severe PMS urinary
problems those kind of things but also
severe panic attacks and agoraphobia to
the degree that she could really not
even leave the house I mean barely even
with her husband so a friend of mine a
colleague of mine was finally asked to
see her he was a psychiatrist I thought
maybe medications would help they really
didn't but I had been working in the
mid-60s on some different kinds of
relaxation techniques using the body and
I had worked with a number of people who
had high blood pressure and what I
discovered was as they had them by hell
them to release certain muscles in their
neck and jaw and shoulders very often
their blood pressure would go down to
normal sometimes 20 or more points from
high to you know to the healthy mid
range so II D my colleague my friend
thought that if maybe I could do some
relaxation with this woman at least that
would help her with her anxiety attacks
so I began the you know getting her to
relax these muscles and and when she
came in I mean her eyes were wide open
deer-in-the-headlight eyes and she was
clinging on to her husband and you could
see they both felt so uncomfortable with
this because you know they were both
burdened in a way by the her the
complete dependency on him anyhow I
started to get and her heartbeat was
going at about a hundred beats a minute
and I could see that and the carotid
pulse so I started to get her to relax
and her heart rate started going down
and down and you know when you're
starting out because I was just starting
to develop these things and in this in
the 60s when you get something that
resembles a success you think oh my gosh
I'm just I'm so smart I really know what
I'm doing
so I had a little dose of that I don't
know what you'd call it but the
delusional attribution but anyhow I got
her to relax and the heart rate started
going down and down and went right to a
normal range and then all of a sudden it
shot up wildly to about a hundred sixty
beats a minute hundred seventy beats a
minute and I mean as I tell you the
story I start to get a little bit you
know my memory starts coming back a
little bit my potty memory and anyhow I
said probably the stupidest thing
anybody could say and that's what I said
which is Nancy you must relax you need
to relax but her heart rate did come
down except it kept coming down so 120
190 70 60 50 and she turned white
and she opened her eyes and they just
grabbed onto mine
in desperation really she said doctor
I'm dying I'm dying don't let me die
help me help me and at that moment might
my chest tighten and I really didn't
know what to do but I did we were
talking about intuition at the time I
didn't know exactly why I did it but
here's what I did
I said Nancy and I pointed to the far
end of the consulting room there's a
tiger there crouched the tiger is ready
to spring run climb those rocks and
escape and to both of our amazements her
legs started moving as though they were
running and we went through different
cycles of her hands turning icy cold and
then warm then there'd be some deep
spontaneous breaths lemon there'd be
sweating and cold again and then to work
more towards warm and over about 30 40
30 30 to 40 minutes
she really settled down and she opened
her eyes she looked at me and she said
do you want to know what happened to me
and like I'm pretending that I know what
I'm doing at this point and I but I said
yes and she said when you told me to run
I started I might rot my body start i
saw the tiger but when my body tried to
run it was like running in quicksand or
under water and i couldn't move but when
you as you continue to encourage me i
could feel myself starting to run i
climbed above the rocks and i looked
down and I saw not the tiger but I saw
myself when I was four years old and I
was held down by doctors and nurses for
a
routine tonsillectomy with ether and at
the time that was that was very commonly
used and she had been utterly terrified
her body had wanted to escape for twenty
years she was 24 when I saw her and then
using that image her body got to execute
that which she had needed to execute
those many many years ago and experience
the the power and and ecstasy of escape
but of her own empowerment and it's that
I'm not saying it's always turns out
like this but that was the last panic
attack anxiety attack that she had we
did a few more sessions to work with
different relaxation and over the pet
necks for 3-4 weeks her physical
symptoms greatly be debated and she was
able to return to graduate school she
was in graduate school ironically in
Physiology so needless to say I was deep
in a life beginning meditation on what
happened why it happened and how could
it be made safe because I realized that
I could have just as easily
retraumatization an Seberg we're talking
about before if the nervous system is
overwhelmed in in terms of how it
perceives things it's not any different
than the than the trauma so so anyhow I
was in I was in graduate school at UC
Berkeley in a department called medical
biophysics which meant I could go to
different like zoology in physics
physiology I could be in these different
areas and nobody knew exactly what I was
doing which was fortunate for me and
anyhow the we were having a seminar with
with one professor and
and he he had been talking about a kind
of a little-known phenomenon where if an
animal is held down which Nancy of
course was by the nurses and thought
leaders of the doctors and nurses they
go into a state called tonic immobility
where they're unable to move it's just
it's a state of paralysis and I realized
that Nancy had gone into that state and
then by using this image I was able to
have her basically escape and mobilize
the energy that had been locked in and
again the key here was now was not just
doing it all at once but but working out
a methodology which ultimately became
somatic experiencing where you you you
you and you take the person to their
difficult sensations one small piece at
a time
I call that titration and they
experienced even though it feels like
they're contracting they'll also be able
to then move into an expansion and a
contraction and akan SPECT and an
expansion I call this potential ation
and these were two of the basic
principles in somatic experiencing to
avoid overwhelm and so again working out
a methodology that I could teach to
people that had those safety features
you know built in we're in this very
polarized time we're all overstimulated
all the time with social media we seem
to be so very stimulated and
disconnected yeah what let light can the
lenses of your work shed on this dynamic
if you're talking to two people who are
in the hyper-vigilant state the
sympathetic adrenal state or the
shutdown state even more so you can't
engage with them because you perceive
them either as threat or as mortal
threat because your nervous system is
stuck in that groove and so there's no
way you can really listen to another
person and and express yourself so they
want to
to you why you're in one of these stuck
states you have to be able to come into
the social engagement system and what's
the link between your work and polyvagal
theory well listen a distinct thing you
know Steve poor Jase and I have known
each other since 1977 and around that
time I was developing somatic
experiencing and I was noticing that
they were seem to be three states that
people were that their nervous system
their bodies would be in the first is
fight-or-flight you know keyed up hyper
aroused hyper vigilant then there was
another one which was really the
shutdown and particular kind of
depression and then there was a state of
being relaxed and calm and being in
contact and so I Stephen Fortas and I
made contact
I sent he sent me an article I sent in
my dissertation and the next week we
were meeting in Los Angeles he was that
he was in Illinois at the time and he
was coming out he first sabbatical well
we probably spent the first 12 hours
just talking non-stop talking nonstop
and we and I I told him about this one
state that I observed where people's
heart beats like Nancy's went down to a
very very low level and and that you
know in order to really work with
somebody you had to be able to get them
out of that state but it was a
parasympathetic state so it was a
reduction in the heart rate and and he
said that couldn't be that
that's impossible then in 1991-92 the
polyvagal theory came out and indeed
they were very these three very distinct
systems and Stephen has made such a
contribution to all the people who are
working in different therapies
particularly into body oriented there
piece and we've stayed close friends for
you know for those many decades could
you talk about like the physiology of
this like what is actually going on when
we're in these conflicts with each other
and when because well I also understand
is that we stop listening to each other
at a certain point when our nervous
system is in the sympathetic arousal
state the fight-or-flight
we will perceive the person there's no
way we won't perceive the person as as
an enemy as an adversary that's just the
way we're wired and again the question
is how we get from there to here here
being social engagement saying look you
know we we recognize there are problems
let's really put our hearts and our
minds together and learn from each other
and contribute to each other and to rich
enrich each other and again the
polyvagal theory gives us a very clear
map of exactly how that works and what
it looks like you can see the facial
expression when somebody's in fight or
foot they're mobilizing the jaw and the
neck is tight when somebody is in a
state of social engagement the eyes are
relaxed and open this part of the of the
the face is is the one that's more
active or the one in more engage okay so
when you're feeling like this you will
not be able to feel like this so so
again we read signals from each other's
faces from each other's postures and if
we consciously subconsciously all the
time we all do it we may not be aware
that we're doing we're all doing it and
so again especially if we're not aware
then we we we don't realize wait a
minute that I'm now in an inner
in an aggressive state and III
aggressive sometimes gets a bad word now
I call about healthy aggression but but
in the state of anger or or fear and
again that's all we'll be able to
experience and this all we'll be able to
perceive and to see but then as we
switch out of those states and come back
to our sense of desiring connection with
others and caring about connections with
others then it's a whole different
ballgame
how do we hack ourselves or hack the
that sort of space of connection okay
the when I started working with people
who have been traumatized this was back
in the sixties the definition of trauma
was still at least 10 12 15 years I you
know in the future so I didn't know
thankfully that trauma was supposedly a
a condition of brain disorder that at
best one could manage so in developing
the tools of somatic experiencing I was
discovering wow these people can really
shift out of these things but they have
to be able to address these sensations
in their bodies because when works when
we experience threat our bodies react or
when we're overwhelmed and shut down our
bodies also react and until we have new
experiences in the body that contradict
the traumatic sensations in our body the
the trauma will continue to play itself
from the past in the present and not
being able to distinguish between the
past and the future having not imagined
being able to imagine a future different
than the past so so it's in in creating
these new sensations so instead of coal
laughs we experience openness and pride
and dignity instead of fighting we we
experience collaboration I mean it
really is that simple
I had a bit of a lightbulb moment on a
it was actually a breath work course
that was informed by somatic
experiencing work and the the
facilitator was using the words be
curious and and there was a real that's
when I really made the link between so
we're we're hosting conversations on
difficult topics and kind of aware that
people can go into a sort of defensive
mode and cure it
as I understand it curiosity is one of
the things that brings us into a contact
can you explain what that means curious
and traumatized at the same time the
physiology that doesn't allow them to
both be there so if you can get the
client enlist the client in being
curious about their sensations and and
and in images and feelings then you've
gotten halfway there really really
because the whole key when you're
curious means you are open to these
sensations you can open into these
sensations rather than defending oneself
against the sensations god if I ever
feel that I'll be completely overwhelmed
and traumatized so we we block them we
suppress them we hold them down and you
know if you hold a powerful sensation
down like this well it pushes back up so
then we perspect even harder to keep it
from pushing up and it pushes up even
harder there's a saying maybe it's from
a a that which we resist persists so the
more we push the more it pushes against
us and then it seems like if we ever let
go we'll be completely overwhelmed but
again if we're able to titrate this if
we're able to do this one small piece at
a time and open to these energies
sometimes I use the slinky you know and
the the energy is like compressed into
this density of energy and what we want
to do is not release that all at
so that that energy just explodes out
like if an animal or the prey animal has
been run down by a predator like a
gazelle with a from a cheetah all of
that energy because they may lay down as
though they were dead and very often the
predator animal will just leave because
they're not interested in an animal that
might be dead because it's possibly
having you know disease but again that
then when when the when the predator
leaves then the prey animal comes back
and just you know bounced away to to
live another day and rejoin the herd but
with with humans we become frightened of
those sensations so again the idea is
just opening to one small amount of
energy at a time and and do that gently
and in a way that the person that is
able to make maintain a curiosity and
we're talking about this in relation to
trauma is there a parallel I'm
suggesting there might be a power at
parallel bit is there a parallel in when
people get locked in kind of ideological
or political conversations well they
feel that they can't will they feel
attacked right exactly they feel
attacked and so they defend themselves
and they found to defend themselves so
they were unable to then engage with the
other you know I mean I think that's the
most common thing we just feel
threatened by someone else's beliefs why
do why does that happen well again I
think it's this the way our nervous
systems are wired because we will can be
in one of these three states I mean we
sometimes go back and forth back and
forth but that's just the way it is
that's where the nervous system works
and again that's the way the body works
because again if we have new experiences
in the body that contradict those of
trauma of fear of rage of helplessness
new experiences that contradict those
experiences then the person moves
through those trauma-based States in
- hey let's get together let's talk I
mean look if you and I you know I I'm
supposed to meet you somewhere and I'm
late and you're angry and if you just
start saying you know god dammit you
told me we're gonna meet here and you
were like half an hour late and my
reaction may be to attack back instead
of saying oh my gosh I'm sorry
god I thought I thought that actually
that I was early you know I thought our
the time we agreed to was such-and-such
the time so we do it we defuse the
situation it rarely does any good if
people who are confronting each other in
fight or flight or in this shutdown
state you know it's an interesting
experiment that Ruth lanius did she's a
one of the leading researchers in trauma
and she showed a picture of a friendly
face a kind friendly open face to a
group of control and these people were
in a very expensive MRI machine brain
scan machine and when they showed the
friendly face that was very interesting
not a surprise that the frontal part of
the brain actually increase in activity
and they've the fear parts of the brain
like the amygdala reduced so then she
showed the very same picture to a group
of people who had experienced chronic
trauma you know and throughout their
childhood and they showed the same
picture and what happens their front
parts of the brain shut down and the
parts of the brain that are involved in
deep fear terror helplessness that tonic
immobility there's an area in the brain
stem called the periaqueductal gray that
part is turned way on so you see the the
the kind face actually then becomes
interpreted as a dangerous face because
the person is in that internal state and
that's the key and I think that's where
Steve and I came together because his
work was saying we have to look at the
environment
does is the environment threatening does
the environment have the the possibility
of more than threat or is it a safe
environment and my way of looking at is
kind of from the opposite is that whoa
if our nervous system is in Moore and
our body is in state fight-or-flight
then we will only experience danger and
so forth so I think it's worth just
unpacking the word trauma in this
context because a lot of people say well
I don't have any trauma or it's a how
are you using that word is it is it in
the way that I understand it which is
just any experience that feels
overwhelming in the moment that is yes
it feels overwhelming and which which
stretches the nervous system beyond its
ability to rebound to reach to rebound
to be rebound resilient Lee and so it
really is about it about and helping the
person develop this capacity for
resilience and Steve calls these neural
exercises and kind of the things that I
do the way he frames it is okay Peter
you have a really great way of evoking
neural exercise with these states so
that instead of being stuck in them we
can be curious oh wait a minute my chest
is tight I feel my jaw tightening I just
need a few moments and then learn I let
those sensations move through and then
I'm able to be present but we have to
take those few moments or we just go
into counter-attack I mean it's really
that's it's that simple
this work is becoming more
scientifically accepted but what of what
are the blocks
is there a kind of is there still a
block around understanding the body's
relationship to the mind or what what
what at one of the what are the cultural
blocks and this becoming more widely
known I mean we are a disembodied
culture and we are a touch deprived
culture and that's the way we have our
first experiences of safety
and the two cultures that are most touch
averse is the United States and even
greater your homeland so so I think
that's a big part of which doesn't give
us this foundation of basic resilience
having the feeling of being safe could
you you mentioned before about the three
that that whether we can take in new
information is related to the the three
different states that we're in could you
just summarize those for us the only
state we can really take in useful
information non threat based information
is the social engagement system what
Steve calls a ventral vagal system the
smart vagus the other two states were
unable to take in new information we are
simply responding as though the threat
that may have happened decades ago is
still playing out in the present and of
course the shutdown state is just
hopelessness we just you know it's just
despair and a deep kind of depression
and again we don't even have any
curiosity or desire even to engage with
somebody and sometimes when the person
that's in the shutdown state they need
to be able to be helped first to move
more into the sympathetic arousal state
the fight-or-flight shake but then to
discharge that to regulate it to down
regulate it and then that naturally
moves into this social engagement
function where we are caring about
ourselves our each other and caring
about the world and how we're going to
leave this world to our children I mean
that's something everybody really in
principle could agree on but again if
we're experiencing the other as
threatening ourselves and threatening
our economic basis then we're not going
to be able to really be open and listen
let's take an example of an argument
between in us in a sort of political
setting or something like that how do we
resource ourselves in the middle of that
how do we put ourselves out of this kind
of spiral well it's good to have these
tools
you know when I started working with men
who were young men it would come back
from the Vietnam War in the 70s one
particular man came in and he he didn't
even sit down he started telling me all
the horrendous things that he did was
made to do or that he he did and when he
he was telling me this I'm like I felt
nausea I felt lightheaded
you know I'm dizzy and I said to him I
said you know Bill when you told me what
you told me I was this is what I started
to feel and it's not because I was
judging you because I know enough about
war to know war is hell but I knew what
to do and I was able to move those
sensations through so I wasn't dominated
by them and I could be here in contact
with you well I had offered to let
people come in to do sessions pro bono
on thursdays and he was the only one
that came in that first thursday
thursday the next thursday where there
was about 25 people going around the
block waiting to come in so we did a
group together to teach people the tools
that they could use to bring themselves
and each other out of these shuts out of
these stuck states and back into flow
you know with really you could say that
we're going with those tools without
those tools trauma rules with those
tools were able to move from fixity to
flow and that's really the gift that we
can give both to ourselves and to others
and what what are those tools that those
tools are to be aware of what goes on in
the body in the moment and allowing that
to shift which it will if we take sort
of a neutral stance to these sensations
they will change if we can become even a
little bit open and curious about these
sensations and feelings they
change that's the way it works if you
know if there was one main discovery of
mine that would be it shift happens if
you know how to reference them in your
body and you can help each other
so imagine instead of attacking and
counter attacking somebody who said gosh
it seems like you're feeling upset I'm
just wondering you know how you
experience that right now and I'm just
be really glad to be here with you while
you're experiencing that well I'm not
different and is it important to name
them at the same time to say this is
what I'm feeling right now in my body
does that is that essential for the
shift was it just just in central just
to notice it the most essential is to
notice it but it is important also to be
able to name it and also to communicate
it you know there's a Motown song it
takes one to stand in the dark alone it
takes two to let the light shine through
so the idea that we can be there for
each other I mean that was the idea of
writing this book trauma proofing here
kids there was a parent's guide for
instilling confidence joy and resilience
because if you teach children how to
move through these scary places then
they will be confident adults confident
caring adults so to me we want to get
these tools out to everybody anywhere
and everywhere do you think that we're
seeing a crisis of meaning well I mean
certainly that that's in play but I
think the crisis is not in meaning but
in being disconnected from our own
aliveness our own vitality and when we
experience our own vitality we want to
share that with others by just by
example in a way you know when you see
somebody who really is present who's
really alive the people are touched by
that they're moved by that so - and when
you when you've been traumatized you
don't feel this you feel threatened
you feel shut down you feel the opposite
of aliveness so do you think we're all
pretty much traumatized in this culture
well I would say so yes yeah I mean
they're different degrees some people
have had the most horrendous things
imaginable happened to them but most of
us have experienced significant amounts
of trauma I mean you know basically our
parents have done the best that they
were able to do but you know these are
things that have hardly been perfect so
it does leave us with with injuries and
maybe these aren't big t traumas of you
know completely overwhelmed but they are
injuries but that's really what trauma
means the definition of trauma is about
injury we have these injuries that add
up over time and these stressors that
add up over time you know and I'm not
talking about you know the everyday
stresses in life which I'm you know but
I'm talking about chronic stress but
sometimes called toxic stress and many
people in their families feel that and
you know and in many cases the parents
don't even have the time to be with
their children I mean you know here you
know they're the safety net is kind of
afraid and so a lot of people you know
if they live in fear of being out on the
street or of having an illness that will
completely bankrupt them so they won't
even you know though they'll lose their
homes and I mean it's really it's a it's
a thing when people feel that degree of
threat they're going to be responding
with the physiology of threat so I mean
what we do have to see what our
priorities are
I mean you you know you're much forged
more fortunate you you live in a country
where we don't you don't have that
degree of a fear of just you know being
out on the streets but in many countries
there you know that is the case your
work is hugely influential within
therapeutic context already where do you
hope it goes next I'd like to see it go
out in the society in general really I
mean that's where we need it I mean
these in my organization now where I've
been talking with the new executive
director really about providing these
skills for people who need it and who
are in different situations like people
in community mental health I'm just
working a little bit with a group of
indigenous people in a mental health in
Alaska I worked in Hopi for a number of
years as well so these are tools that
belong to humanity I mean I mean I just
happened to stumble along that across
them but I think they're what you could
call you know the perennial philosophy
the perennial understanding of what it
means to be human
rebel wisdom is an Eve sense-making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon